Inventory to the Records of the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP) (1970-1985)
Sophia Smith Collection
Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project records
1970-1985
Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project
MS 310
46 boxes (29.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Documentation program. The Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project Records include correspondence, speeches, legal documents, photographs, press releases, reports, articles, interview transcripts, audio and video tapes, legislative records, logbooks, notes, documentary footage, and memorabilia. The bulk of the records comprise audiovisual materials from two documentaries: "Who Will Protect the Family," Victoria Costello's PBS documentary based on the 1982 North Carolina ERA campaign; and "Fighting for the Obvious" based on the Chicago, Illinois, ERA campaign produced by Virago Video, and ERACAP. There is also considerable material relating to the National Organization for Women's work to pass the Equal Rights Amendment. Additional ERA-related materials collected by Beth Leopold are included. Notable individuals included in the documentary footage are: Susan Cantinia, Dennis Cuddy, Donald Deuster, Frances Fitzgerald, Jesse Helms, Wilma Scott Heide, Peggy Madigan, Lamarr Mooneyham, Kathy Railsback, Phyllis Schlafly, Ellie Smeal, Gloria Steinem, and Monica Faith Stewart.
The Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) was first introduced in the U.S. Congress in 1923. It was introduced in every session of Congress after that for nearly half a century. In 1971 the House of Representatives approved the proposed amendment. The Senate approved the amendment a year later. The issue was sent to the state legislatures and twenty states ratified the ERA almost immediately (Alaska, Colorado, Delaware, Hawaii, Idaho, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, Nebraska, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, Tennessee, Texas, West Virginia, and Wisconsin). In 1973 Connecticut, South Dakota, Oregon, Minnesota, New Mexico, Vermont, Washington, and Wyoming ratified; Nebraska voted to rescind its ratification. Over the next few years, Maine, Montana and Ohio voted to ratify and Tennessee voted to rescind. In an effort to gain the additional three votes necessary for ratification, groups with many pro-ERA supporters boycotted states that had failed to ratify the Amendment. As the deadline for ratification loomed (22 March 1979), Representative Elizabeth Holtzman (D-NY) introduced a bill to extend the deadline for ratification. In October of 1978, Congress set a new deadline for the ERA--30 June 1982. In 1980 Ronald Reagan became the first president since the Equal Rights Amendment was sent to the states to oppose the ERA. On 30 June 1982 the ERA died, falling three states short of the necessary three-fourths ratification.
Beth Leopold worked on the National Organization for Women (NOW) campaign to ratify the ERA. After its defeat, she sought to ensure that the story of the fight for ratification would be preserved and began the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP). The goal of the ERACAP was to "collect and process oral history and photographic materials relating to the ERA campaign between the years 1970 and 1982." The focus of the collecting was on the experiences of participants in the local, state, and national levels of the campaign.
The aim of the original project was to interview 150-200 people involved in the pro or anti-ERA work using archival quality open reel audiotape and to make typed transcripts of the interviews. There were also plans to create an index of the subjects covered in the interviews, along with photographs and a directory for additional materials related to the ERA campaign. Because funding for the project ran out in 1984, the oral history interviews were never created; however, Beth Leopold acted as intermediary between the Sophia Smith Collection and two documentary filmmakers to house their tapes and accompanying printed matter within the ERACAP collection. "Who Will Protect the Family?" was completed and aired on PBS in 1982. "Fighting for the Obvious" (Virago Video, 1982) was also completed, but it is uncertain whether it was shown by a major media outlet. In addition, Leopold's own ERA-related material came with the ERACAP materials.
The ERACAP Records consist of 29.75 linear feet and are primarily related to the fight to ratify the Equal Rights Amendment between 1972 and 1982. Types of materials include correspondence, speeches, legal documents, photographs, press releases, reports, journal and newspaper articles, transcripts of interviews, audiocassettes, videocassettes, legislative records, logbooks, notes, documentary footage, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the records comprise audiovisual materials documenting the ERA fights in Illinois and North Carolina from two documentaries, Fighting for the Obvious and Who Will Protect the Family?. There is also considerable material relating to the National Organization for Women's work to pass the Equal Rights Amendment.
Notable individuals included in the documentary footage are: Alan Alda, Birch Bayh, Susan Cantinia, Midge Costanza, Dennis Cuddy, Donald Deuster, Frances Fitzgerald, Jake Garn, Jesse Helms, Wilma Scott Heide, Peggy Madigan, Lamarr Mooneyham, Kathy Railsback, Phyllis Schlafly, Eleanor Smeal, Gloria Steinem, and Monica Faith Stewart. A portion of the footage for each documentary has been reformatted to DVD viewing copies.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. ERACAP ADMINISTRATION
II. NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN AND THE ERA
III. WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY? DOCUMENTARY FILES
IV. ERA DEFEAT
V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the exception of audiovisual materials that have not been reformatted for use by researchers. Viewing copies for selected footage are available on DVD.
Additional Formats
A sample of original video footage for both documentaries has been reformatted and viewing copies are available as digital files and on the SSC website (on-campus access only). See Appendix for descriptions of reformatted footage.
Lynn Kanter (Virago Video) donated the audiovisual materials from Fighting for the Obvious in 1984. Beth Leopold donated her personal papers and the records of ERACAP as well as Victoria Costello's materials relating to Who Will Protect the Family? to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1988.
Equal rights amendments--Illinois--History--Sources; Equal rights amendments--North Carolina--History--Sources; Equal rights amendments--United States--History--Sources; National Organization for Women--History--Sources; Oral history--methodology; Women's rights--United States--History--Sources; Family--Social aspects--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project; Moral Majority, Inc.; Fitzgerald, Frances, 1940-; McAllister, Beth; Schlafly, Phyllis
APPENDIX: DOCUMENTARY SUMMARIES
WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY?
This footage is from the 1982 hour-long PBS documentary that examines both sides of the ERA fight in North Carolina. According to the official press release from the filmmaker, Victoria Costello, Who Will Protect the Family? "is an intimate, personal, political chronicle of the last three years [1979-1982] in the controversial struggle in North Carolina between the political organizations and individual activists of the conservative, born-again, Christian political movement, and the liberal women's movement."
Reporter Frances Fitzgerald is a Pulitzer Prize-winning author, and Victoria Costello is an independent video producer based in Washington, D.C. Together, they gained behind-the-scenes access to political meetings, lobbying efforts, and the workplaces and homes of those involved in both sides of the struggle. The central focus of the documentary is the "evolving lives of two North Carolina activists," Beth McAllister, a feminist, and Marilyn DeVries, a conservative Christian. Other footage includes a Christian high school graduation, the first pro-ERA march ever held in North Carolina; a Father's Day service at the church of Reverend Lamarr Mooneyham, the Chairman of North Carolina's Moral Majority; a Father's Day picnic, organized by Black feminists in the Black community of Raleigh; and several personal confrontations between conservative and feminist movement members and leaders.
* In addition to these footage excerpts, the Sophia Smith Collection also has a copy of the documentary in its entirety.
Individuals Appearing in Footage
Alan Alda Actor/ERA activist
Pat Blackstone Pro-ERA organizer, Hickory, North Carolina
Rep. Louise Brennan North Carolina Legislature
Phyllis Clay Beautician, Hickory, North Carolina
Dr. Dennis Cuddy Anti-Abortion activist, Raleigh, North Carolina
Marilyn DeVries Anti-ERA activist
Miriam Dorsey N.C. Council on the Status of Women
Employees of Ridgeview Hosiery Hickory, North Carolina
Hugh Gaither Owner, Ridgeview Hosiery, Hickory, N.C.
Alice Wynn Gatsis Chairwoman, N.C. United Against ERA
Senator Rachel Gray North Carolina Legislature
Richard Hatch WUNC-TV/PBS, Raleigh, North Carolina
U.S. Senator Jesse Helms Republican, North Carolina
Jackie Kaaland ERAmerica
Senator Craig Lawing President Pro-Tempore, NC Legislature
Beth McAllister Pro-ERA activist
The McAllister Family Raleigh, North Carolina
Rev. H. Lamarr Mooneyham State Chairman, N.C. Moral Majority, Inc.
League of Women Voters Hickory, North Carolina
Phyllis Schlafly Eagle Forum, Inc.
Eleanor "Ellie" Smeal NOW
Rev. Robert Settle & Family Hickory, North Carolina
Gloria Steinem MS. Magazine
Tabernacle Baptist Church Hickory, North Carolina
Tri-City Baptist Church Durham, North Carolina
Paul Weyreich Committee for Survival of a Free Congress
FIGHTING FOR THE OBVIOUS
Fighting for the Obvious focuses on the fight for the ERA in Illinois, another key state in the battle for ratification. The footage features many pro-ERA activists and legislators, and their struggle to get the ERA ratified, and also includes interviews with anti-ERA legislators and protestors. Filming locations include the Illinois Legislature, activists' homes, and outdoor rally locations.
*The ERACAP Records do not include a final version of Fighting for the Obvious, and we have been unable to locate a copy. As far as we know, this footage is all that remains.
Individuals Appearing in Footage
Mary Brandon Work Coordinator, Chicago NOW Chapter
Rep. Susan Catania Pro-ERA Illinois Republican Representative
Anne Courtney Leader of a local IL NOW Chapter/ERA Coalition
Rep. Donald Deuster Anti-ERA Illinois Republican Representative
Wilma Scott Heide Feminist/ERA activist
Clara Johnston Pro-ERA activist
Kristen Lems Singer-songwriter from Evanston, Illinois
Peggy Madigan Volunteer organizer for Chicago NOW Chapter
Linda Miller Co-Director of ERA Countdown Campaign
Kathy Railsback Member of Chicago NOW Chapter
Phyllis Schlafly Anti-ERA conservative leader
Carol Swinney Outreach Coordinator of NOW
REFORMATTED VIDEO FOOTAGE: DESCRIPTIONS
[NOTE: These videos are available as digital files and on the SSC website (Smith campus access only)]
WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY?
#1, "Anti-ERA Group, Pt. 2, n.d."
An anti-ERA group is interviewed at a STOP ERA rally in front of the North Carolina Legislature in 1979. Phyllis Schlafly and her involvement in the STOP ERA campaign and her anti-ERA views are discussed, as well as women and social security, women and work, the family and the ERA, affirmative action, and the International Women's Year.
#2, "GARN press conference and pt. 1 of Bayh press conference (#16), n.d."
US Senators Birch Bayh and Jake Garn, among others, discuss ERA and its constitutionality, rescission and amendment of the bill, and women and the military draft.
#3, "Gloria Steinmen [Steinem] interview - phone calls (#17), n.d."
Gloria Steinem is interviewed in Washington, D.C. in 1979. She discusses speaking at the Joan of Arc Church in Minneapolis about religion and the ERA, as well as the difficulty of organizing a grassroots letter campaign for the ERA. She mentions Coretta Scott King's meeting with Senator Birch Bayh regarding the Humphrey Hawkins Bill and the ERA extension vote. She also discusses her concerns about the Florida ERA vote and the voting practices taking place in FL.
#4, "Gloria Steinmen [Steinem] interview, end; beginning of victory party for House extension, n.d."
*Sound does not work from 2-minute mark to 4:30-minute mark.
After the House of Representatives' vote on the extension of the ERA Bill in Washington, D.C. Pro-ERA interviews include Gloria Steinem. Issues discussed are abortion and the Right to Life Amendment, Kate Millett and Sexual Politics, and Eleanor Smeal's ERA contributions.
#5, "Excerpts from PBS abortion show, 1979"
Excerpts from a PBS documentary on abortion. Topics include clergy people for the restoration of government funded abortions, computer technology, abortion lobbying, abortions and class structure, mass mailings, Richard Viguerie and the New Right, and single-issue groups.
#6, "Marilyn and Bob at home pt. 1, 1979"
Interview with Marilyn and Bob DeVries at their home in 1979 as part of Victoria Costello's documentary. Marilyn and Bob DeVries discuss Alice Winn Gatsis, North Carolinians against ERA, the Humanist Manifesto, family structure and lesbian mothers, The Spirit of Houston, the First National Women's Conference, Beth McAllister and North Carolinians for ERA, Senator Billy Mills, media bias towards ERA (more coverage of pro-ERA, William Ball, Esq. (a constitutional lawyer investigating ERA), and appointments and delegations to the International Women's Year.
#7, "ERA Song, 1978"
At a 1978 NOW Conference, songs performed are "Take a Look at my People," about the black community and ERA, by an unknown performer. Kristen Lems, a founder of the National Women's Music Festival, performs "Mammary Glands" and "ERA Ballad." Individuals appearing include Gloria Steinem, Penny Rosenwasser, and Dean Mackey. "Friday's Victory" and five years of ERA rallies are discussed.
#8, "Scott interview, pt. 2; Aurabelle [Laurabelle Yoder] after vigil (#8), n.d."
In 1979, members of Congress discuss the constitutionality of extending ERA for 7 years, and instead compromise on a 3-year extension to 1982. Issues discussed are rescinding of state ERA, the predicted outcome of the ERA, interest and popular involvement around ERA, and Senator Birch Bayh's forum on ERA voters. Interview with Senator Bill Scott of the Virginia Dept. of Navy, Airforce, Marine Corps, and Army, about ERA. Pro-ERA students lobby. Interview with Laurabelle Yoder, local ERA lobbyist in North Carolina.
#9, "vigil and GARN interview, pt. 1 (#9)"
ERA Rally on the steps of the United States Congress in 1979 before the 3-year extension of the bill. Discussion of the Mormon Church and pro-ERA members, the Mormon Constitution, ERA extension, ERA vs. opposition to equal rights, constitutionality of extension, sex discrimination, and the status of women. Individuals appearing include Sonya Johnson of the Mormon Church (before her ex-communication), Senator Hatch of Utah, and Senator Garn of Utah.
#10, "TCI taping of WRAL show, 'Pro and Con,' (#4), n.d."
Discussion of the pros and cons of the ERA from anti- and pro-ERA view on the television show "Pro and Con" aired on NBC's WRAL channel in 1979. Individuals appearing include Beth McAllister and Alice Winn Gatsis. Issues discussed are Alice Paul and the beginning of the ERA, rescinding of ratified state ERA, ratification of national ERA, public hearings in the NC general assembly, equal rights versus the ERA, upholding the nuclear family structure, protection for women, and the 14th Amendment.
#11, "Gloria Steinem interview (#19), n.d."
On the steps of the United States Congress, individuals speak about the 1979 vote to extend the ERA in the senate. Individuals appearing are Gloria Steinem and Laurabelle Yoder. Discussion includes grassroots support, Ellie Smeal and the NOW Action Center, and the votes of Senators Holtzman and Edwards. On Part 2 of the DVD, Gloria Steinem discusses people against women's autonomy in the home, ERA and its lack of impact on abortion laws, family values, child support, divorce, and marriage as an equal partnership.
#12, "Marilyn and Bob @ home, pt. 2, n.d."
Bob and Marilyn DeVries are interviewed at home in North Carolina in 1978 for "Who Will Protect the Family?" Pros and cons of ERA are discussed, such as southern voters and the ERA, God and the creation of the family, how Marilyn got involved in the anti-ERA movement, North Carolina churches and the ERA, the laws that already exist to protect the family and equality, media treatment of the ERA, the draft, and the economy.
#13, "Ellen Goodman abortion show PBS, 1979"
This DVD is an excerpt from a PBS show on abortion with Ellen Goodman in 1978. Discussions include the impact of minority groups and single-issue voters in national votes, the Right to Life Amendment, the right to privacy, Roe v. Wade and its affect on privacy, the correlations between conservative views and abortion, pro-choice as pro-family, the fetus having more "protected rights under the law" than an adult, Gallup poll on abortion, and safe, legal abortions.
#14, "Gloria Steinem interview (#18), n.d."
This interview with Gloria Steinem takes place before Congress voted to extend the ERA ratification deadline. Steinem discusses the votes in Florida, as well as the possibilities for ratification in Illinois, Florida, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Arizona. Also covered is the state legislature ratification process; D.C. voting rights; ERA and economics; ERA, the Mormon church, and the Utah legislature; misleading syntax and names of laws and bills; public opinion polls; extension and the economic boycott; what will happen if extension fails; media and the treatment of ERA; divided voters; and discrimination lawsuits.
#15, "Beth and Marilyn, hallway conversation (#5), n.d."
Beth McAllister and Marilyn DeVries have a discussion in the hallway of WRA: 5 TV, North Carolina (ABC) after the taping of the show "Pro and Con" with Alice Winn Gatsis and Beth McAllister in 1979. They discuss the conflicting Supreme Court precedent around the ERA, ERA and homemakers, family life and structure and the ERA, ERA as a "communist" document, NOW and radicalism, sexual morality, and religion and the ERA.
#16, "Gloria Steinem interview, summertime on the lawn (#3), n.d."
Gloria Steinem is interviewed after the House of Representatives' extension on the ratification of the ERA. She discusses Congresswoman Holtzman's stance on the ERA, how her life experiences have affected her feminist views, feminism's portrayal in the media and the press, her creation of Ms. Magazine, and the ERA march in Washington D.C. in 1979.
#17, "Weddington and Sonya interview (#21), n.d."
Sonya Johnson is interviewed in Washington, D.C. before her excommunication from the Mormon Church. She discusses the church's lack of support of the ERA and she also discusses the Potomac Area LDS Women's Coalition. In all fifteen unratified states, women from the Mormon congregations go to organizational meetings and teach women how to lobby against the ERA using John Birch Society materials from Phyllis Schlafly. She also discusses the power and financial prowess of the Mormon Church in its anti-ERA activities, but also mentions that the president of the LDS has not yet spoken out against ERA.
#18, "ERA supporters office (#19), 1979"
Supporters volunteer at a phone bank for the ERA in Raleigh, NC in 1979. Issues discussed are lobbying women around the state to contact their local governments in support of ERA, and the logistics behind phone-a-thons and mass mailings.
#19, "Hall outside committee room (#16), 1979"
Beth McAllister is interviewed after the North Carolina Senate Committee on Constitutional Amendments killed the ERA bill in its first session. Senator Rachel Gray is interviewed as well, and expresses hope for the next vote. Pitt County and Martin County Representatives who opposed the ERA are interviewed. There are also local news station interviews with Beth McAllister and anti-ERA representatives.
#20, "Beth and group outside after vote (#17), n.d."
*Footage stops after 9 minutes.
Beth McAllister and other pro-ERA women are interviewed outside of the North Carolina legislature. They discuss the North Carolinian defeat of the ERA and their hopes for the future.
#21, "WPJL radio show pt 3 (#8), 1979"
Marilyn DeVries and Alice Winn Gatsis continue their WPJL radio call-in show. Topics include state vs. federal ERA bills, homosexual marriage, and legal cases regarding the ERA (Henderson v. Henderson).
#22, "Beth at home (#9), n.d."
Beth McAllister and her husband are interviewed at home about the ERA Campaign in late 1978/early 1979. Issues discussed are the upcoming Senate vote and the General Assembly Constitutional Committee meeting at the NC legislature, the process of lobbying government officials, morality and ERA, and Senator Rachel Gray's support of the ERA.
#23, "ERA supporters in their offices (#10), n.d."
Continuing footage of volunteer ERA supporters at a phone bank in Raleigh, NC in 1979. Topics include potential strategies, and the votes of various politicians. Jessie Rae Scott is also interviewed briefly.
#24, "Jessie Rae Interview (#11), n.d."
Jesse Rae Scott is interviewed in 1979. She discusses phone banks urging citizens to send messages to legislatures, grassroots lobbying efforts such as letter writing campaigns, her own meetings with the governor and legislators, misconceptions about the ERA, planning for the ERA public hearing which were to include speakers such as Dr. William Aycock, a law professor at UNC Chapel Hill, and Dr. Perry Young of Duke University, a minister who spoke on career planning.
#25, "Jessie on the phone in Miller's office (#12), n.d."
Jessie Rae Scott telephones various people to ask for their support of the ERA bill. She calls Dr. Winston and asks him to speak at an ERA hearing. She also discusses Cecil Hill, Dr. Young, and Dr. Aycock.
#26, "Rachel Gray's office canvassing before the vote, n.d."
Beth McAllister, Jesse Rae Scott, Miriam Badowski, Susan Green, and Senator Rachel Gray converse in Gray's office at the NC legislature building in 1979, discussing the upcoming ERA vote in the NC Constitutional Amendments Committee later that morning. They anticipate that the ERA would be temporarily defeated for two years and speculated that the committee does not want the bill to get as far as the state senate. Other issues mentioned are meetings with Cecil Hill, chair of the Constitutional Amendments Committee, and meetings with the other members of the Committee.
#27, "Craig Lawling [Lawing] interview (#14), n.d."
"Stop ERA" supporters discuss their views. Governor Robert Scott reflects on the defeat of the ERA and his hopes for the future of the bill. Beth McAllister and Senator Craig Lawing discuss his formal support of the bill.
#28, "Beth McAllister and group at lunch, newsroom (#15), n.d."